Guide to the Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design,Corcoran Gallery of Art education department records 1961-2010 COR0006.0.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art education department records
circa 1961-2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
COR0006.0.RG
105 Linear Feet
In 1955 a small group of volunteer women began guiding tours through the Corcoran Gallery of Art. This initial docent program was successful but could not be adequately administered by the Curator whose other Gallery responsibilities were equally demanding. It became obvious to the Women's Committee that the existing tour program could only be met by the establishment of a permanent office with a full-time staff. The Women's Committee argued and generously supported the view that the Corcoran needed an Education department, not only to administer the docent program but also to help play up the importance of the Gallery as a center of American art. Consequently, on June 15, 1967, ten years after the inception of the initial docent program, the Education Department began with Roger Selby as Curator of Education. The records cover all aspects of the Education Department's operation and administration and include: docent notebooks and training material; intern notebooks and training material; proposals to create an education department; standard operating procedures; budgets; grant proposals and funds; correspondence; activities notebooks; resource notebooks; school workshops; public liaison committee; school tours program; lesson plans and notes for school tours; programs offered; exhibition labels and research materials; film lists; lectures and lecture possibilities; publicity; and bibliographic material.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to research.
When conducting research within The Corcoran Archives collections, pleased be advised of the following exceptions:
Records of the Board of Trustees (RG 1.0) and records of the Office of the Director (RG 2.0) are closed to research for 25 years from the date of creation.
Development records are closed to research (RG 3.2).
Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for the lifetime of the student, and are presumed to be open 75 years after the date of record creation (RG 9.0 Series 4).
Personnel and financial records are closed for 50 years from date of record creation (RG 4.0).
Please see the Public Services and Instruction Librarian for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Corcoran Institution Board of Trustees donated these records to The George Washington University in 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into 21 series [Note series 1-13 were processed in 1984 and series 14-21 were processed in 2016]: Administration, Finances, Correspondence, Docents, Interns, Activities notebook, Schools, Programs, Exhibitions, Films, Lectures, Publicity, Miscellaneous, Administration files, Admissions files, Audio visual content, Events, Exhibitions, Grants, Programs, and Tours, interns, publicity files
Historical narrative
The first section of this history, covering events through 1981, was prepared by Corcoran Archivist Katherine M. Kovocs for publication in 1985 with the support of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
In 1955 a small group of volunteer women began guiding tours through the Corcoran Gallery of Art. This initial docent program was successful but could not be adequately administered by the Curator whose other Gallery responsibilities were equally demanding. It became obvious to the Women's Committee that the existing tour program could only be met by the establishment of a permanent office with a full-time staff. The Women's Committee argued and generously supported the view that the Corcoran needed an Education department, not only to administer the docent program but also to help play up the importance of the Gallery as a center of American art. Consequently, on June 15, 1967, ten years after the inception of the initial docent program, the Education Department began with Roger Selby as Curator of Education.
The major tasks of the Education Department at its inception were many. An important step was to overhaul the docent program -- to review scheduling procedures, to determine the number of docents the Corcoran needed, to outline the requirements necessary for docentry, and initiate formal and informal docent training in order to ensure quality performances. As well as being responsible for docent selection, training, assignments, and discharge, the Education Department was responsible for the selection, organization, and content of the tours conducted by the docents. With this end in mind, Roger Selby, the first curator, began to build a slide collection to use in docent training and in the Art History courses which he was first the teach in the Corcoran School of Art. Another important task of the Education Department was to explore new developments in education via consulting with educators and institutions and to represent the Corcoran Gallery of Art as an educational advisor. To this end, the Women's Committee with a generous donation from Mrs. John A. Logan, and in conjunction with the Education Department, created the Children's Gallery in 1966.
Established in Gallery 50, the Children's Gallery - filled with tables and chairs - served as a display area as well as a workshop. Through the Children's Gallery, the Education Department offered a series of correlated exhibitions related to school curricula which were supplemented by the use of films, demonstrations, participation and lectures; a series of workroom sessions for different age groups giving opportunities to paint, model, make prints, weave, make pottery and explore all other crafts; a series of special events designed to take advantage of transient opportunities to enliven and expand the regular program. Though the Children's Gallery itself was phased out, the Corcoran Education Department maintained a viable and lively workshop designed to complement the curricula of the D.C. area public/private schools. The Education Department also offered the extension of various services to the educational community from the Gallery resources. For instance, the setting-up and circulating of prefabricated small exhibitions to schools and the maintenance and circulation of good quality reproductions to be available on long-term loans to decorate school assembly halls and classrooms on a yearly or half-yearly basis.
A further task of the Education Department was community outreach. The Special Education project first started as an adjunct to the Education Department in 1968, and had the task of formulating and implementing an intensive, comprehensive community outreach program for the Corcoran Gallery of Art. In 1969, a new department, under the curator of education, was formed extending full recognition to the first year of experimental programming. Special Education organized specialty outreach workshops on painting, drawing, sculpture, graphics, design, photography, film-making, and creative puppetry. The Special Program department worked with settlement houses, community centers, Capital Headstart, National Capital Housing Authority, National Parks Service, Minimum Security Detention Center at Lorton, Va., Neighborhood Youth Corps, and Workshops for Careers in the Arts.
To enhance the Corcoran's public image, the Education Department inaugurated various Wednesday Gallery talks and initiated the first European Art Seminars, and tours for members.
The Education Department always sought ways in which to involve the public as participants rather than just onlookers in their visits to the Corcoran Gallery. In planning programs that would introduce processes of art, as well as art history, the department hoped to encourage awareness of the activity of creating and the thought involved in art creation. The Education Department endeavored to present an appropriate introduction to the Gallery for each age level, a unique visual experience that engages the viewer and one that would encourage him to return, and the development of the Gallery as a resource of original art works and the means to use that resource.
The following section of this history was prepared in 2019 by George Washington University SCRC staff with the support of the Luce Foundation.
For a time the Education Department was responsible for both the Annual Report and graphics for the Gallery, but was eventually able to pass those jobs to other more appropriate departments. Responsibility for graphics, in particular, was handed over to the Public Relations department.
During the 1980s the Education Department began to focus more heavily on programming connected to special and temporary exhibitions. These programs and events related to the themes of the exhibition and included evening lecture series, children's craft programs, and programs aimed at teachers and educators.
The Education Department created a sister group to the Corcoran Docents in 1983 by adding a corps of individuals from the Junior League of the District of Columbia who staffed the museum's information desk. They also gave weekend introductory tours about the museum's permanent collection and collected a written comment and complaint log to assist with visitor feedback. The Department was also responsible for several branches of the Corcoran's internship program, including undergraduate, graduate, and high school level opportunities
In 1988, the Education Department launched "We the People", which consisted of three American art and art history programs with a focus on inclusive and diverse stories. These programs included sections on portraiture, landscape painting, and still life, and brought a variety of teaching aids that included art reproductions, color slides, and classroom materials into D.C. area schools. Expansion of the program in 1990 added in-school visits, museum tours, and art-making studios. This program reached over 27,000 students annually.
During this time, the department's adult education programs moved from Wednesday to Thursday, and came to include Art & Co, a lecture and film series for the city's working community.
The Education Department also worked for several years on generating informative in-gallery labels for the permanent collection as part of the gallery's push in the late 1990s and early 2000s to become an intellectually accessible museum.
Throughout the 2000s, the department continued to create evening programs as well as educational materials tied to specific exhibitions. At this time, the department also began to integrate in-school materials with exhibition-specific programing, creating educational materials that teachers could continue to use after the trip to the Gallery. This initiative expanded into a summer Teachers Institute.
The department ended its functionality when the Gallery was partitioned in 2014, although a Continuing Education department does still exist as part of the Corcoran School of the Art and Design, focusing on non-credit art and design courses for adults of all ages.
Custodial History
The records of the Education Department were transferred to the Corcoran Archives from storage beginning in January 1980, and intermittently since then, directly from the Education Department.
Scope and Contents
The creation of the Education Department in 1965 coincided with the conviction on the part of the Corcoran that a museum art gallery should be more than a repository for precious objects, but rather, that is should be a force in moving art from its ''exclusive" status to a position of general availability to the public. With this goal in mind, the Education Department developed art experiences for Washington area young people and adults that are a crucial mixture of workshop activity and exposure to original works of art. The records of the Education Department reflect its desire to provide an operational base for the crucial mixture of basic art history, the museum process, and the workshop process. The records cover all aspects of the Education Department's operation and administration and include: docent notebooks and training material; intern notebooks and training material; proposals to create an education department; standard operating procedures; budgets; grant proposals and funds; correspondence; activities notebooks; resource notebooks; school workshops; public liaison committee; school tours program; lesson plans and notes for school tours; programs offered; exhibition labels and research materials; film lists; lectures and lecture possibilities; publicity; and bibliographic material.
Names that are prominent in the Education Department records are: Roger L. Selby Sue Ann Hoth David Stevens Susan Gans Donna Ari Theresa Simmons Barbara Moore
Separated Materials
The following records were discarded: various unrelated correspondence, duplicate correspondence (Xerox & carbon), interdepartmental memos, time sheets, budget work sheets, outdated mailing lists, addresses and directories, old program information requests, tour requests, reservations and schedules, school calendars and docent training and tour schedules. During the processing the following records were removed to another location: -Photographs to Archive audio-visual records -Catalogs to Curatorial publications -News clippings to Artists vertical files and history clipping files -News releases to P.R. press release series
- Series 1-13 note about content please read
  - Administration [1984 processing project], 1963-1983; Series 1; 18 Cubic Feet
    Arrangement
    Organized into 4 subseries: Organization; Committees, meetings, councils; Operation; and Personnel
    - Organization, 1965-1983; Series 1 Subseries 1
      Scope and Contents
      This subseries contains proposals for the setup of the Education Department, standard operating procedures, annual reports and statistics, history of the Education Department, and suggestions for improving the organizational structure.
    - Committee, meetings, councils, 1970-1975; Series 1 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains information on Trustee Education Committee minutes, Education Department Committee minutes, Museum Education Roundtable, Community Resources, Educational Research Council, Energy Crisis and Museums, V.C.A.M. Conferences, Computers and Resources, correspondence, minutes, sub-committee reports, research articles, miscellaneous goals and objectives.
    - Operation, 1961-1983; Series 1 Subseries 3
      This subseries contains schedule forms and scheduling procedures, information on Museum training programs, special projects (PACE, 370, Lorton, etc.), proposals and programming and chronological files.
    - Personnel, 1970-1981; Series 1 Subseries 4
      This subseries contains staff regulations, information on job recruitment for Administrative Assistant and a Projects Aide, volunteers, weekly worksheets, and evaluations and evaluation forms.
  - Finances [1984 processing project], 1966-1982; Series 2; 1 Cubic Feet
    Organized into 2 subseries: Fiscal year budgets, and Grants
    - Fiscal year budgets, 1966-1973; Series 2 Subseries 1
      This subseries contains information on cash flow, curator of budgets, accounting reports, insurance forms.
    - Grants, 1974-1982; Series 2 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains correspondence, applications, budgets and reimbursement-records associated with various grants: HEW Special Project Grants, Helena Rubenstein Grant, Rockefeller Foundation, Noble Foundation, D.C. Fine Arts Commission, N.E.H., N.E.A., Federal Aid Project, National Foundation, for Arts and Humanities.
  - Correspondence [1984 processing project], 1964-1978; Series 3; 1 Cubic Feet
    This series contains general correspondence, correspondence dealing with particular seasons, membership letters, and "fan mail."
  - Docents [1984 processing project], 1966-1979; Series 4; 11 Cubic Feet
    Organized into 5 subseries: Notebooks, Docent training, Docent administration, Docent personnel and Docent tours
    - Notebooks, 1970-1971; Series 4 Subseries 1
      This subseries contains copy of invitation to become a docent, a reading list, selected bibliography on art historical topics, correspondence, docent responsibilities, history of the Corcoran with overview and responsibilities of the various departments, information on tour techniques, guidelines for conducting tours, notes on the permanent and changing exhibitions, docent exam.
    - Docent training, 1969-1978; Series 4 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains correspondence, training schedules, lecture materials, biographical materials on artists, questionnaires, self-tours, quizzes, docent skills workshop, information on other docent programs.
    - Docent administration, 1969-1978; Series 4 Subseries 3
      This subseries contains development report, Treasurer's report, docent's annual report, attendance reports, monthly and weekly time schedules, staff meeting minutes, correspondence between docents and various Corcoran departments.
    - Docent personnel, 1969-1978; Series 4 Subseries 4
      This subseries contains director's letter to docents welcoming them to the Corcoran, docent applications and rejections, docent recruitment procedures and correspondence, and personnel files on each docent containing evaluation, exam score, correspondence and schedules
      Conditions Governing Access
      This subseries may contain materials with private personnel information that is restricted. All requests to use materials in this series must be approved by Public Services and Instruction Librarian.
    - Docent tours, 1969-1978; Series 5 Subseries 5
      This subseries contains tour procedures, and files of tours given by docents.
  - Interns [1984 processing project], 1967-1982; Series 5; 2 Cubic Feet
    Organized into 3 subseries: Notebooks, Administration, and Personnel
    - Notebooks, 1975-1979; Series 5 Subseries 1
      This subseries contains orientation handouts, correspondence, training program, intern reports, journal of the intern process, planning handbook, magazine/research articles on art historical topics.
    - Administration, 1975-1982; Series 5 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains annual reports, quarterly reports, bi-monthly reports, tri-weekly reports, and final reports. All reports are directly related to the intern and summer intern program.
    - Personnel, 1967-1982; Series 5 Subseries 3
      This subseries contains personnel file folders on interns containing correspondence, applications, evaluations, schedules, financial benefits and recommendations.
      This subseries may contain materials with private personnel information that is restricted. All requests to use materials in this series must be approved by the Public Services and Instruction Librarian.
  - Activities notebook [1984 processing project], 1975-1977; Series 6; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains bibliographies on art historical subjects and descriptions of school programs, adult programs, children's activities, gallery information. Informative guide to what kinds of activities the Education Department offered.
  - Schools [1984 processing project], 1964-1976; Series 7; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains correspondence with schools in the Washington area, tour write-ups for the 4th, 5th, and 6th grades, lesson plans, notes, teacher information packets, teacher evaluations of tours, programs, tours, workshops, ideas, and planning lists.
  - Programs [1984 processing project], 1967-1980; Series 8; 0.75 Cubic Feet
    Organized into four subseries: Tours, Workshops, Dance, and General programs
    - Tours, 1967-1978; Series 8 Subseries 1
      This subseries contains correspondence, itineraries, and general information on European Art Seminar tours; contains information on self-guided tours of the Corcoran, studio visits, walking tours, and architectural tours.
    - Workshops, 1970-1980; Series 8 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains correspondence, planning lists, schedules, sign-up forms for workshops put on by the Education Department, such as: Workshop for Career in the Arts, The Workshop, the Pre-school workshop, Sunday membership workshops, Parent-Child workshops, Children's Sunday workshops.
    - Dance, 1974; Series 8 Subseries 3
      This subseries contains correspondence, scheduling, programs, and advertising for the Dance Circus and the Experiment in Dance Theater.
    - General programs, 1972-1981; Series 8 Subseries 4
      This subseries contains correspondence, schedules, advertisements, planning notes on such programs as Parent-Child Treasure Hunt, George Washington University Matt series, and the Junior League Educational Program.
  - Exhibitions [1984 processing project], 1972-1982; Series 9; 1 Cubic Feet
    Organized into two subseries: Labels and paintings lists and Individual exhibitions
    - Labels and paintings lists, 1972-1982; Series9 Subseries 1
      This subseries contains lists of art paintings in Corcoran collection and the drafts of labels written for art paintings hung in exhibitions at the Corcoran. Served as examples of how to do labels.
    - Individual exhibitions, 1972-1982; Series 9 Subseries 2
      This subseries contains information sheets, labels for the individual exhibitions, research articles/materials, programs, handwritten working notes, press-release copy, inter-office memos and correspondence.
  - Films [1984 processing project], 1961-1970; Series 10; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains correspondence, programs, film lists, price lists, and memos.
  - Lectures [1984 processing project], 1961-1969; Series 11; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains correspondence, memos, programs, budgets, announcements, and lecture possibilities lists, for lecture series and Wednesday Gallery talks.
  - Publicity [1984 processing project], 1972-1976; Series 12; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains brochures, publications, publicity, and newsletter copy, as well as correspondence between the Public Relations Department and the Education Department.
  - Miscellaneous [1984 processing project], 1965-1982; Series 13; 0.25 Cubic Feet
    This series contains resources notebook, Women's Committee minutes, various bibliographic material, slide orders and correspondence, information on the audio system, lists of art work reproduced for teaching and lecture aids.
- Administration files [2016 processing project], Circa 1963 - Circa 2012; Series 14
  Arranged in original order.
  - Education Department Reports, 1977-1978; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Special Projects Grant - HEW, 1979 March; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Arch is Elementary" Final Rept. - Redskins Foundat., 1978-1979; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grant: Helena Rubenstein, Undated; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1982 June 28; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grant Proposals C. School - Alumni, 1978; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D/A's Proposal for Ed Dept., Undated; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Docentry recruitment, press campaign, 1971-1972; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Records, 1969-1972; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education Proposals, 1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Corresp. w/ Art Supervisors, 1970-1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women's Committee, 1970-1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Special Projects, 1968-1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Addresses, Directories, 1969-1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bibliographical Materials, 1970-1971; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gallery Announcements & PR, 1971-1972; Series 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)